Finding Aid for Warren P. Lombard papers, 1877-1939
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Warren P. Lombard papers 1877-1939
Lombard, Warren P. (Warren Plimpton), 1855-1939.
(in 4 boxes)
3 linear feet
85811 Aa 2
Professor of physiology at the University of Michigan; correspondence, speeches, and other materials concerning U-M Medical School activities, the Ann Arbor Red Cross, the Ann Arbor Art Association, and Lombard’s interest in art and etching.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of the estate of Warren P. Lombard, Alfred H. White, executor (donor no. 983 ) and came to the library in multiple accessions, 1940-1941.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Warren Plimpton Lombard was born in West Newton, Mass., on May 29, 1855. He received his bachelor of arts degree from Harvard College in 1878 and his medical degree from Harvard Medical School in 1881. He studied at Leipzig and Turin and taught at Clark University and the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Columbia University before coming to the University of Michigan in 1892 as Professor of Histology and Physiology. In 1898, Lombard's title was changed to Professor of Physiology and Director of the Physiological Laboratories. He retired from the University in 1923.
Lombard was a charter member of the American Physiological Society, of which he was president in 1919, and he also belonged to the Society for Experimental Biology and Medicine, the American Association for Advancement of Science, and the University Research Club. He was a corresponding member of the Societe de Biologie and an associate member of the Societe Royale des Sciences Medicales et Naturelles de Bruxelles.
In his retirement years, Lombard developed his interest in etching. He would become an active member of the Ann Arbor Art Association up until his death July 13, 1939.
The Warren P. Lombard papers have been arranged into the following series: Biographical/miscellaneous; Correspondence; Organizational and other interests; Physiology and related materials; and Photographs. Much of the collection relates to Lombard's organizational activities, notably the Ann Arbor Red Cross and the Ann Arbor Art Association. Some of Lombard's correspondents include: James B. Angell, William W. Bishop, Marion L. Burton, James J. Couzens, John G. Curtis, Joseph Erlanger, Frederick R. Green, Charles W. Greene, Granville S. Hall, Yandell Henderson, Donald R. Hooker, Frederic S. Lee, Carl Ludwig, Graham Lusk, George W. Norris, Reuben Peterson, William T. Porter, Henry Sewall, Albert A. Stanley, Langdon C. Stewardson, and Victor C. Vaughan.
Subjects:
American National Red Cross. Ann Arbor Branch.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor Art Association.; Art.; Lombard, Warren P. (Warren Plimpton), 1855-1939.; Medicine--Michigan.; Physicians--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Red Cross and Red Crescent--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Physiology.; University of Michigan. Medical School.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Lombard, Warren P. (Warren Plimpton), 1855-1939.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.; Burton, Marion Le Roy, 1874-1925.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Curtis, John Green, 1844-1913.; Erlanger, Joseph, 1874-1965.; Green, Frederick Robin, 1870-1929.; Greene, Charles Wilson, 1866-1947.; Hall, G. Stanley (Granville Stanley), 1844-1924.; Henderson, Yandell, 1873-1944.; Hooker, Donald Russell, 1876-1946.; Lee, Frederic S. (Frederic Schiller), 1859-1939.; Ludwig, Carl, 1816-1895.; Lusk, Graham, 1866-1932.; Norris, George W. (George William), 1861-1944.; Peterson, Reuben, 1862-1942.; Porter, William Townsend, 1862-1949.; Sewall, Henry, 1855-1936.; Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.; Stewardson, Langdon Cheeves, 1850-; Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Prints.
- Biographical/miscellaneous
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
    (file no. 1)
  - Miscellanea (Box 1)
    (file no. 2)
- Correspondence
  - 1877-1899 (Box 1)
    (file no. 3)
  - 1900-1909 (Box 1)
    (file no. 4)
  - 1910-1919, concerning in part Ann Arbor Civic Association (Box 1)
    (file no. 5)
  - 1916, concerning reunion of the University of Michigan Medical School Class of 1891 (Box 1)
    (file no. 6)
  - May 1919-December 1920, relating to opening of Information Service of Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (Box 1)
    (file no. 7)
  - June 1919-October 1920, relating to founding of Physiological Reviews (Box 1)
    (file no. 8)
  - July 1919-December 1920, relating to Council of American Physiological Society (Box 1)
    (file includes notes)
    (file no. 9)
  - November 1919-June 1920, relating to International Physiological Congress (Box 1)
    (file no. 10)
  - November 1919-December 1920, relating to American Journal of Physiology (Box 1)
    (file no. 11)
  - November 1920-January 1921, concerning founding of Porter Fellowship of the American Physiological Society (Box 1)
    (file no. 12)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
    (file no. 13)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
    (file no. 14)
  - 1922, including letter of resignation from The University of Michigan (Box 1)
    (file no. 15)
  - 1923, including incorporation of American Physiological Society in Missouri (Box 1)
    (file no. 16)
  - 1924 (Box 1)
    (file no. 17)
  - 1925 (Box 1)
    (file no. 18)
  - 1926 (Box 1)
    (file no. 19)
  - 1928-1929 (Box 1)
    (file no. 20)
  - 1930-1938 (Box 1)
    (file no. 21)
  - Correspondence with A.A. Stanley 1911-1924; also obituary of Stanley, 1933 (Box 1)
    (file no. 22)
- Organizational and other interests
  - Ann Arbor Red Cross 1917-1927, 6 folders (Box 1)
    (file nos. 23-28)
  - European Relief Fund 1920-1921, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (file nos. 29-30)
  - Art Clubs (Box 1)
    (file no. 31)
  - Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters; articles on art (Box 1)
    (file no. 32)
  - Etching techniques and materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
    (file nos. 33-34)
  - Newspaper Clippings concerning etching (Box 1)
    (file no. 35)
  - Lists of etchings by Lombard 1916-1938 (Box 1)
    (file no. 36)
  - Lists of art purchased by Lombard 1923-1936 (Box 1)
    (file no. 37)
  - Lithographic techniques (Box 1)
    (file no. 38)
  - Ann Arbor Art Association 1925-1927 (Box 1)
    (file no. 39)
  - Ann Arbor Art Association, Committee on Financial Aid 1925-1927 (Box 1)
    (file no. 40)
  - Ann Arbor Art Association exhibits 1922-1936 (Box 1)
    (file no. 41)
  - Ann Arbor Art Association history (Box 1)
    (file no. 42)
  - Exhibitions of work 1926-1938, 7 folders (Box 1)
    (file nos. 43-49)
- Physiology and related materials
  - Printed material of ninth International Physiological Congress, Groningen 1913 (Box 2)
    (file no. 50)
  - Laboratory class notes in Physiology 1904-1905 (Box 2)
    (file no. 51)
  - Physiological research notes, 4 folders (Box 2)
    (file nos. 52-55)
  - Notes and experiments on fatigue, 7 folders (Box 2)
    (file nos. 56-62)
  - Notes on physiological effects of cigar smoking (Box 2)
    (file no. 63)
  - Paper, "Influences affecting voluntary muscles, American Physiological Society 1915 (Box 2)
    (file no. 64)
  - Graphs recording muscle fatigue of A. Stanley playing organ (Box 2)
  - History of the department of physiology (Box 2)
  - Sign-out book: department of physiology library (Box 2)
  - Class book 1902-1903 (Box 2)
  - Notes on balance (Box 2)
  - Scientific diagrams, etc. (Box 4)
  - Budgets and other materials: department of physiology (Box 3)
  - 1995 accession (unsorted) (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Portraits (Box 3)
  - Other photographs (Box 3)
  - Prints (Box 3)
  - Copy prints (from Horace Davenport) (Box 3)
  - Copy negatives (from Horace Davenport) (Box 3)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1926.
July 2, 1892 [3]; June 30, 1893 [3]; Jan. 1, 1900 [4]; June 30, 1907 [4]
Bishop, William Warner, 1871-1955.
Aug. 27, 1923 [16]
Burton, Marion LeRoy, 1874-1925.
Mar. 2, 1922 [15]; June 23, 1922 [15]; Dec. 11, 1922 [15]
Couzens, James, 1872-1936.
Dec. 9, 1920 [29]; Dec. 13, 1920 [29]; May 26, 1921 [30]
Curtis, George William, 1824-1892.
Letters, May 9, 1877 and Feb. 3, 1878 from G.W. Curtis; also autographed oration, 1877, by Curtis.
Curtis, John Green, 1844-1913
Jan. 5, 1888 [3]
Erlanger, Joseph, 1874-1965.
Nov. 17, 1919 [8]; Jan. 15, 1920 [7]; May 19, 1920 [10]; June 11, 1920 [10]; Nov. 15, 1920 [13]; Nov. 26, 1920 [12]
Green, Frederick Robin, 1870-1929.
July 8, 1919 [5]; July 14, 1919 [5]; July 21, 1919 [5]
Greene, Charles Wilson, 1866-1947.
June 20, 1919 [8]; July 2, 1919 [5]; July 18, 1919 [5]; October 27, 1919 [8]; Dec. 4, 1919 [9]; Dec. 8, 1919 [9]; Jan. 21, 1920 [8]; May 28, 1920 [11]; June 19, 1920 [11]; Sept. 7, 1920 [11]; Nov. 15, 1920 [13]; Nov. 20, 1920 [12]; Apr. 6, 1921 [14]; June 30, 1921 [14]; Aug. 7, 1924 [17]
Hall, G. Stanley (Granville Stanley), 1844-1924.
June 20, 1988 [3]; Aug. 4, 1888 [3]
Henderson, Yandell, 1873-1944.
June 7, 1920 [10]; Nov. 28, 1920 [12]
Hooker, Donald Russell, 1876-1946.
June 23, 1919 [8]; Nov. 5, 1919 [8]; Nov. 19, 1919 [11]; Dec. 17, 1919 [11]; Feb. 26, 1920 [11]; May 12, 1920 [11]; May 29, 1920 [8]; June 24, 1920 [11]; Oct. 1, 1920 [8]; Oct. 23, 1920 [8]; Dec. 16, 1920 [11]; Dec. 18, 1920 [11]; May 17, 1924 [17]
Lee, Frederic S. (Frederic Schiller), 1859-1939.
Nov. 10, 1919 [10]; Feb. 13, 1920 [10]; Apr. 13, 1920 [10]; May 18, 1920 [10]; June 25, 1920 [10]; Aug. 5, 1920 [10]; Dec. 3, 1920 [10]; Dec. 5, 1920 [10]
Ludwig, Carl, 1816-1895.
1885 (1), 1886 (3), 1888 (5), 1890 (1), 1891 (1), 1892 (1), 1893 (1), 1894(1), 1895 (1), 1896 (from Ludwig's widow)
Lusk, Graham, 1866-1932.
Oct. 24, 1918 [5]; Jan. 28, 1919 [5]
Norris, George W. (George William), 1861-1944.
July 22, 1919 [5]
Novy, Frederick George, 1864-1957.
Letter, June 30, 1907, from J.B. Angell discussing an offer Novy has received.
Osler, Sir William, 1849-1919.
Letter of Sir William Osler, undated
Peterson, Reuben, 1862-1942.
Apr. 10, 1919 [5]
Porter, William Townsend, 1862-1949.
Jan. 24, 1905 [4]
Sewall, Henry, 1885-1936.
Aug. 18, 1909 [4]
Stanley, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1851-1932.
1912-1924 [22]
Stewardson, Langdon Cheves, 1850-
Apr. 30, 1907 [4]; Aug. 26, 1909 [4]; May 27, 1921 [14]; Apr. 1, 1922 [15]
Vaughan, Victor C. (Victor Clarence), 1851-1929.
June 11, 1892 [3]; Oct. 26, 1921 [14]
Wenley, Robert Mark, 1861-1929.
In Lombard's resignation folder [15]